<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE xtiny-doc-page SYSTEM "../dtd/xtiny-doc-page.dtd" >

<!--
  -
  - Jext documentation source document
  - Based on xtiny-doc DTD
  -
  - DTD:xtiny-doc and XSL:xtiny-doc
  - are (C)1999 Romain Guy
  -
  - Last updated: 12/02/2001 - 22:54:51
  -
  -->

<xtiny-doc-page author="Romain Guy"
           update="12/02/2001"
           name="Jext : Search"
           title="Search And Replace"
           prev="jext-editor.html"
           next="jext-console.html">

  <paragraph title="Overview">
    The <b>Search</b> menu of the Jext menubar provides features to find and/or replace text in
    your documents. There are six search/replace functions. Three of them only are
    described in this page; the others are explained in the
    <a href="jext-menus-search.html">Search Menu</a> page.
  </paragraph>

  <paragraph title="Find">
    The <b>Find</b> item displays the Jext find dialog box. In this dialog box, three components
    are grayed: they are activated only if you need to perform a replace operation. To perform
    a search, simply enter your search pattern in the text field, then press the <b>Find</b>
    button. Please note the text field remembers of the 25 last typed search pattern.
  </paragraph>
  <paragraph>
    Next to the find button, there is a <b>Cancel</b> button. Pressing this button simply disposes of 
    the dialog box. And finally, there are 4 check boxes at the bottom of the dialog. Those items
    allow you to modify the way the search and replace operations are performed:
    <menu>
      <item name="Ignore Case">
        If checked, the case of the letters will be ignored. For instance, using the search
        pattern <b>java</b> and assuming this item is checked, pressing find button will
        report <b>JAVA</b> as a match.
      </item>
      <item name="Save values">
        If this item is checked when you quit the find/replace dialog, then Jext will remember
        your settings the next time you use the dialog.
      </item>
      <item name="In All Files">
        Performs the search/replace operation in all the open files.
      </item>
      <item name="Use Extended RegExp">
        By default, Jext does a plain search. If you check this box, Jext will instead use the
        Perl5 syntax for extended regular expressions, which can be used to perform powerful searches.
      </item>
    </menu>
  </paragraph>

  <paragraph title="Replace">
    Clicking the <b>Replace</b> menu item displays the same dialog box as the <b>Find</b> item.
    All the features described in the Find section are still available. Using the <b>Replace</b> 
    button will replace the current match then look for next one. Also, 
    the <b>Replace All</b> button will invoke replacement of all the matches without asking
    anything, so take care if you checked the In All Files option. As for the Find feature, the
    replace text field remembers the last 25 typed patterns.
  </paragraph>
  <paragraph>
    You can also use the <b>Script</b> function. This function allows you to replace every 
    match made by a regular expression with the result of the evaluation of a Python script.
    For instance, if you look for the regular expression <i>&lt;([^&lt;&gt;]*)&gt;</i>, Jext will
    attempt to find any single HTML tag. If you use the <b>Script</b> option with this value:
    <i>"&lt;" + _m[0].upper() + "&gt;"</i> and then press <b>Replace All</b>, Jext will replace
    any single HTML tag by the same, changed to uppercase. Just know the <b>_m</b> object is an array containing
    the matches of groups of the regular expression.
  </paragraph>

  <paragraph title="Find All">
    Even though the <b>Find All</b> dialog box is slighty different from the find/replace one,
    most of the features are the same. That's why Ignore Case, Use Extended RegExp
    and the text field behave the same way in both dialogs. Whenever you perform a Find All
    operation, all the matches are displayed in a list. Clicking an item of the list directly
    brings you onto the match, selecting it in your document.
  </paragraph>
  <paragraph>
    To easily browse through the matches, you can check the option Highlight. If checked, all
    the matches will be underlined in blue in your document.
  </paragraph>
</xtiny-doc-page>

<!-- End of Jext documentation -->
