<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE xtiny-doc-page SYSTEM "../dtd/xtiny-doc-page.dtd" >

<!--
  -
  - Jext documentation source document
  - Based on xtiny-doc DTD
  -
  - DTD:xtiny-doc and XSL:xtiny-doc
  - are (C)1999 Romain Guy
  -
  - Last updated: 12/02/2001 - 22:21:33
  -
  -->

<xtiny-doc-page author="Romain Guy"
           update="12/02/2001"
           name="Jext : Menus"
           title="Menus"
           prev="index.html"
           next="jext-menus-file.html">

  <paragraph title="Overview">
    Jext Menus benefit from a little explanation. Although they are similar to menus 
    you see in many applications (Word, Gimp, etc...), Jext menus have an interesting feature
    which you usually find only in applications such as Emacs/XEmacs... Here's how such menus
    work.
  </paragraph>
  <paragraph>
    Each main menu (File-Edit-Search-Plugins-Jext) contains menu items (ex: Select All in Edit
    menu) and can contain a number of submenus (for instance the submenu Recents in main menu
    File). You pulldown main menus by simply clicking on them, or by using the keyboard shortcut
    <b>Alt+LETTER</b>, where LETTER is the underlined letter of the targeted menu. Because it is
    used so often, the File menu can be activated with the <b>F10</b> key.
  </paragraph>
  <paragraph>
    Once you've pulled down the desired menu, select your menu item of choice to fire the desired
    action or hover your mouse over a submenu (represented by a little arrow on right) to unroll
    it. You may notice that some menu items have blue text displayed on their right. This serves
    as a reminder of the keyboard shortcut which activates this menu item. Using keyboard
    shortcuts can greatly improve your productivity.
  </paragraph>

  <paragraph title="Menu items keyboard shortcuts">
    Keyboard shortcuts look like this: <b>C+e</b>. <b>C+e</b> means hold the Control key down and
    press e. There are two other modifiers: <b>A</b> which stands for the <b>Alt</b> key and
    <b>S</b> which stands for the <b>Shift</b> or <b>Meta</b> key. They can be combined:
    <b>CA+s</b> means hold down both Control and Alt, then press s.
  </paragraph>
  <paragraph>
    Sometimes you'll find strange keyboard shortcuts (Emacs users already know these). Take
    <b>C+e C+m</b> for example. This means that to activate the corresponding item you have to hold
    down Control, press e and then press m.
  </paragraph>

  <paragraph title="Repeating actions">
    In the Edit menu the Delete Line item is activated by pressing C+d. Now imagine you would 
    like to delete 10 lines at once... You could press C+d ten times but this is not efficient
    and we programmers abhor repetitive, brain-dead tasks. After all, that's what computers are
    for, right? Use action repetition instead and make Jext do your work for you!
  </paragraph>
  <paragraph>
    So, you want to delete 10 lines. Simply press <b>C+ENTER 10 C+d</b>. This sequence must be
    done like this: hold down Control and press ENTER, release Control, type 10 on your numeric
    pad on the keyboard, hold down Control and press d.
  </paragraph>
  <paragraph>
    Of course, this trick works with any number, not just 10. Even better, this trick works with
    any keyboard shortcut as well.
  </paragraph>
</xtiny-doc-page>

<!-- End of Jext documentation -->
