<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE xtiny-doc-page SYSTEM "../dtd/xtiny-doc-page.dtd" >

<!--
  -
  - Jext documentation source document
  - Based on xtiny-doc DTD
  -
  - DTD:xtiny-doc and XSL:xtiny-doc
  - are (C)1999 Romain Guy
  -
  - Last updated: 12/02/2001 - 22:20:47
  -
  -->

<xtiny-doc-page author="Romain Guy"
           update="12/02/2001"
           name="Tools Menu"
           title="Jext : Tools Menu"
           prev="jext-menus-search.html"
           next="jext-menus-plugins.html">

  <paragraph title="Overview">
    The <b>Tools</b> menu contains miscallenaous tools.
  </paragraph>

  <menu title="Contents">
    <submenu title="Dawn">
      <item name="Execute">
        Executes the current text area content as a script.
      </item>
      <item name="Run Script">
        Lets the user choose a file to run as a script.
      </item>
      <item name="Log Window">
        Opens the scripting log window which keeps a trace of the latest executed scripts. It is very
        useful when you activate the Dawn server.
      </item>
    </submenu>
    <submenu title="Python">
      <item name="Execute">
        Executes the current text area content as a Python script.
      </item>
      <item name="Run Script">
        Lets the user choose a file to run as a Python script.
      </item>
      <item name="Log Window">
        Opens the scripting log window which keeps a trace of the latest executed scripts. Please report to this
        window when an error occures.
      </item>
    </submenu>
    <item name="Zip As">
      Zips (i.e. packs or compresses) the current document into a specified zip file. Be careful!
      If you specify an existing zip file, it will be overwritten. The document needs to be saved
      before being zipped: see Save As or Save.
    </item>
    <item name="Mail To">
      Displays the Jext mail dialog. You need to enter your email address(ex:
      john.smith@yeah.gov), your SMTP server adress (ex: mail.yeah.gov) and the destination
      email. All these settings are saved for future sessions. When you're done with these
      settings, press Send and Jext will mail the contents of the active Jext window.
    </item>
    <item name="Split/Unsplit Editor">
      Triggers the split feature. When the text area is split, you are allowed to edit the same
      document in two text areas. Thus, you can read one part while editing another.
    </item>
    <item name="Trigger Left Panel">
      Triggers the left panel which contains by default the XTree and some plugins.
    </item>
    <item name="Trigger Right Panel">
      Triggers the console panel.
    </item>
  </menu>
</xtiny-doc-page>

<!-- End of Jext documentation -->
